Guide to the Elizabeth (Beth) York Papers, 1970-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Elizabeth York papers 1970-1998
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
York, Beth.
1.5 Linear Feet 900 Items
Musician and music therapist.
Collection includes manuscripts, sound recordings, and photographs from York's music career, with materials from her participation at the 1986 International Music Festival; press kits with photographs and reviews of her music; contracts and agreements from Ladyslipper Inc.; and materials relating to her album Transformations, released in 1985.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Elizabeth York Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Dr. Elizabeth (Beth) York (b. 1949) is a Board Certified Music Therapist as well as a musician and performer. Originally from South Carolina, she graduated from the University of Georgia with a Bachelor of Music degree in music therapy in 1972. She later earned her Ph.D. in music education from the University of Miami. Throughout the 1980s, she worked as a performer, a music therapist in various mental health centers, and a music instructor. Her first commercial recording, Transformations, was distributed by Ladyslipper beginning in 1985, and was nominated by the National Association of Independent Record Distributors as a Best New Age Recording.
More recently, York has served as director of the music therapy program at Utah State University, and is currently the chair of music education and therapy at Converse College in Spartanburg, South Carolina.
Collection Overview
Collection includes manuscripts, sound recordings, and photographs from York's music career, with materials from her participation at the 1986 International Music Festival; press kits with photographs and reviews of her music; contracts and agreements from Ladyslipper Inc.; and materials relating to her album Transformations, released in 1985.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
York, Beth
Transformations.
Women musicians
Women singers
Ladyslipper, Inc
Feminist music
Audiocassettes
Phonograph records
Photographs
Negatives
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
Related Material
Ladyslipper, Inc. Records
Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture, Duke University.
Contents of Collection
- Music materials, 1970-1998, (1 box)
  Original audio materials are CLOSED to use. Please contact the Rubenstein Library in advance if you are interested in hearing this material.
  - Anima Rising, Atlanta, Georgia, 1978-1985 (Box 1)
    Separated recordings are in Box 2.
  - First National Congress of Women in Music, March 1981
  - Aurora, 1987-1988
    Includes cassette tape.
  - Artist correspondence, 1983-1988
  - Collaborations with Kay Gardner (letters and scores), 1985-1998
  - International Women's Music Festival correspondence, Israel, 1986-1988, (2 folders and 1 t-shirt)
  - Investor letters, 1983-1985
  - Kay Gardner memorials
  - Ladyslipper, Inc., 1985-1986
    Includes contract, promotions, reports, and 1 cassette tape.
  - Miscellaneous artist contracts, 1985
  - Miscellaneous performances, 1982-1987
  - Miscellaneous therapy workshops, early vita, and letters, 1970-1988
  - Performance contacts, 1983-1987
  - Photographs and pictures from concerts, promotions, and rehearsals
  - Miscellaneous photographs and negatives, 1978-1985
  - Press kit materials, 1985
  - Projects and grant proposals, 1979-1987
  - Southern Arts (media and education project) concert, 1989 October 21
  - Transformations, first concerts, 1981-1983
  - Transformations, Ladyslipper, 1985-1986
  - Transformations, reviews and articles, 1983-1987
  - Women's music business, 1984-1986
  - Test presses of records (3 records) (Box 2)
  - Transformations title drafts and notes